Scholar, convict, leader, disciple, hipster, father,
hustler, minister, black man, every man.
Malcolm X is a drama, history film directed by Spike Lee.
A tribute to the controversial black activist and leader
of the struggle for black liberation.
He hit bottom during his imprisonment in the '50s, he became a
Black Muslim and then a leader in the Nation of Islam.
His assassination in 1965 left a legacy of self-determination and racial pride.
Malcolm X, played by Denzel Washington.
Betty Shabazz, played by Angela Bassett.
Baines, played by Albert Hall.
Elijah Muhammad, played by Al Freeman Jr..
West Indian Archie, played by Delroy Lindo.
Shorty, played by Spike Lee.
Malcolm X is a 1992 American epic biographical drama film
about the African-American activist Malcolm X.
Directed and co-written by Spike Lee, the film stars Denzel Washington in the title role,
alongside Angela Bassett, Albert Hall, Al Freeman Jr., and Delroy Lindo.
Lee has a supporting role, while Black Panther
Party co-founder Bobby Seale, the Rev.
Al Sharpton, and future South African president
Nelson Mandela make cameo appearances.
The screenplay, co-credited to Lee and Arnold Perl, is based largely on
Alex Haley's 1965 book The Autobiography of Malcolm X.
Haley had collaborated with Malcolm X on the book beginning in
1963 and completed it after Malcolm X's death.
The film follows key events in Malcolm X's life: his criminal career, his incarceration, his conversion to Islam, his ministry as a member of the Nation of Islam and his later
falling out with the organization, his marriage to Betty X, his pilgrimage to Mecca and reevaluation of his views concerning whites, and his assassination in 1965.
Defining childhood incidents, including his father's death, his mother's mental
illness, and his experiences with racism are shown in flashbacks.
Malcolm X was distributed by Warner Bros.
and released in the United States on November 18, 1992.
The same year, Denzel Washington won the New York Film Critics
Circle Award for Best Actor for his performance.
At the 65th Academy Awards, the film was nominated for two Oscars including the
Best Actor for Washington and Best Costume Design for Ruth E.
In 2010, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of prison, new york city,
police brutality, beach, assassination.
The tone is dark and emotional.